<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.cafelinear.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.cafelinear.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-13T23:28:22-03:00</updated><id>https://www.cafelinear.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Café Linear</title><subtitle>F: Coffee ↦ Software</subtitle><author><name>Douglas Drumond Kayama</name></author><entry><title type="html">Opportunity Solution Tree</title><link href="https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/13/opportunity-solution-tree.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opportunity Solution Tree" /><published>2022-01-13T23:26:29-03:00</published><updated>2022-01-13T23:26:29-03:00</updated><id>https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/13/opportunity-solution-tree</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/13/opportunity-solution-tree.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;opportunity-solution-tree&quot;&gt;Opportunity Solution Tree&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever tried to brainstorm ideas to find what to work on next? And you
ended up with too many ideas that you had to aggressively trim down or, worse,
you solved the wrong problem? Opportunity Solution Tree may help you avoid
that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opportunity Solution Tree (let’s shorten it to OST) is a visual way to
represent how the solutions connect to the desired outcome in a way that helps
you focus on solving the right problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can build an OST in 4 steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Identify the outcome, e.g., a metric you want to improve. Example: improve
engagement on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Find opportunities related to your desired outcome. Example: build
relationships with other creators.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brainstorm the solutions with one condition: the solutions should always be
linked to one of the opportunities from the previous step. Example: comment
on other people’s tweets. An example of what not to do: start another
account in another social network.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Define experiments to validate your hypothesis. Example: engage with at
least 3 other creators per day for two weeks and compare how received likes,
retweets and followers changed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that in step 2 you may find more than one opportunity, thus in step 3
you create solutions for several opportunities, increase the options to
multi-track, i.e., act on more than one opportunity at a time. You don’t fixate
on one opportunity. However, you’re always connected to your goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reframing the ideation process using the OST framework allow you to find
solutions without going off course or creating too much noise. Give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@halacious?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Hal Gatewood&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/s/photos/diagram?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Douglas Drumond Kayama</name></author><summary type="html">Opportunity Solution Tree</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Extreme Ownership</title><link href="https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/12/extreme-ownership.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Extreme Ownership" /><published>2022-01-12T12:45:29-03:00</published><updated>2022-01-12T12:45:29-03:00</updated><id>https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/12/extreme-ownership</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/12/extreme-ownership.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;extreme-ownership&quot;&gt;Extreme Ownership&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first got a leadership role, I asked a friend for tips to learn and do
my job better. He referred me to a book, Extreme Ownership, by Jocko Willink
and Leif Babin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book’s main idea is to take ownership of everything you do (or don’t do),
especially for a leader. If a team fails, the leader should step up and
assume the failure instead of blaming the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this idea is relevant for individual contributors too. Instead of blaming
others, look at what you could have done better to prevent the situation.
Instead of “the budget approved by C-level wasn’t reasonable”, think of “what
can I do with this budget and how can I bring visibility of possible
shortcomings?” Instead of “the tasks are not well described”, think of “what
questions can I ask to clarify the requirements?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when a problem arises, do not point fingers. Assume the failure, learn
from it and create an action plan to do better next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extreme ownership is not an excuse to be dumb, though. If you’re innocent,
don’t take the blame for something illegal. Those infringing the law must
face the consequences, not you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time you face an issue, instead of pointing fingers, try this exercise:
ask yourself, “what could I have done to prevent this?” And act on the
conclusion. You’ll notice that, after a while, you’ll earn more trust from
your team, peers and leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@specna_arms_4s?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Specna Arms&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Douglas Drumond Kayama</name></author><summary type="html">Extreme Ownership</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gear with sould</title><link href="https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/08/gear-with-soul.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gear with sould" /><published>2022-01-08T23:12:29-03:00</published><updated>2022-01-08T23:12:29-03:00</updated><id>https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/08/gear-with-soul</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/08/gear-with-soul.html">&lt;p&gt;Does gear have a soul?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I watched a YouTube video from Ted Vieira, a well-known photographer among the Fujifilm community, titled Gear With Soul? He shows a magazine by KEH Camera with the tagline “Gear with soul for people with vision” and spends the video showing photos and talking about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also an old video from DigitalRev TV where Kai Wong discusses what makes a Leica M unique. And the very last line is “it got soul.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember being in a workshop and the instructor badmouthing Sony cameras saying “they have no soul”. A friend of mine joked “of course not, they are cameras!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do some people say that some objects have souls? I have seen this also happening in motorcycle community and I found a pattern. Beware this is not a scientific study, everything is based only on anecdotal evidence. Both in motorcycle and photography community, it’s usually related to old or at least old-style cameras or motorcycles. It makes me wonder if it’s just a nostalgic feeling for people who lived in a bygone era or younger people who wished to live in that era or just people running away from the day-to-day rush and those objects remind them of a slow-paced time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it’s just baloney, but if you feel inspired by that, go ahead. Enjoy the way the camera feels in your hands, the lens, moving the focusing tab. Pretend you’re Sebastião Salgado, Henri Cartier-Bresson, Robert Capa and go have fun with your camera. Who knows what kind of photography you’ll get in those unpretentious moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@lekhang?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Le Khang&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Douglas Drumond Kayama</name></author><summary type="html">Does gear have a soul?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Working through change</title><link href="https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/05/working-through-change.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Working through change" /><published>2022-01-05T23:12:29-03:00</published><updated>2022-01-05T23:12:29-03:00</updated><id>https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/05/working-through-change</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cafelinear.com/2022/01/05/working-through-change.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It’s not the strongest of the species that survives, nor the most intelligent; it is the most adaptable to change.”&lt;/em&gt; This quote is often misattributed to Charles Darwin (it first appeared in a speech by Leon C. Megginson in 1963).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That quote refers to the evolution of the species, but we can bring it to the corporate environment, especially in the startup world. Companies pivot. Companies fail. Companies merge and get acquired—the culture of the company changes. For better or for worse, but it won’t stay the same. Some people can’t accept that. It’s ok to dislike the change and move to another company. People have different preferences and are suited to different environments. But if you’re resilient and can bear with the change, it can be an excellent opportunity to grow in your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to perform well when everything is going well but harder to stick out because everyone is doing alright. On the other hand, when the company is going through change, and people start to complain, just show up and work. Of course, you can complain about the problems but use the proper channels. Chances are, your manager is also trying to avoid the dismantling of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you survive those challenging moments, you’re seen as reliable and may be assigned more responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that the only way to grow or get more responsibilities? No. Are you wrong if you leave? Definitely no. No company is worth your mental health, and if it’s terrible for you, move on. Be true to yourself. You’re not better or worse if you stay or if you go. But while you’re there, do your best and try to get the best from the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@grimstad?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Håkon Grimstad&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/s/photos/change?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Douglas Drumond Kayama</name></author><summary type="html">“It’s not the strongest of the species that survives, nor the most intelligent; it is the most adaptable to change.” This quote is often misattributed to Charles Darwin (it first appeared in a speech by Leon C. Megginson in 1963).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One-on-one meetings</title><link href="https://www.cafelinear.com/2021/03/28/one-on-one-meetings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One-on-one meetings" /><published>2021-03-28T21:38:29-03:00</published><updated>2021-03-28T21:38:29-03:00</updated><id>https://www.cafelinear.com/2021/03/28/one-on-one-meetings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.cafelinear.com/2021/03/28/one-on-one-meetings.html">&lt;p&gt;You can’t simply gain trust by saying “trust me, I know what I’m saying”, you have to earn it. Let’s start discussing trust and then how to conduct one-on-one meetings to earn that trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trust&quot;&gt;Trust&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2021/01/mistrust/&quot;&gt;The High Price of Mistrust&lt;/a&gt;, a book titled Bowling Alone, by Robert Putnam, is discussed and there are two parts I’d like to quote as they relate to remote management:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“One key lesson we can derive from Bowling Alone is that the less we trust each other—something which is both a cause and consequence of declining community engagement—the more it costs us.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Mistrust drives us to install remote monitoring software on our employees’ laptops and ask them to fill in reports on every tiny task to prove they’re not skiving off.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveillance is an attempt to control the team. That’s the wrong premise, you don’t have to control the team, you have to build trust, provide directions and trust the team will do the right thing. And to build trust, first you start building relationships. But how to do that without face-to-face interactions like you had at the office? One-on-one meetings are the key to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-one-on-one-meetings&quot;&gt;Why one-on-one meetings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Google, it was believed that to be a good engineering manager, having deeper technical expertise than the team was needed. Still, what they found through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/13/business/13hire.html&quot;&gt;Project Oxygen&lt;/a&gt;, a 2009 manager research project, was that the most valued managers were the ones who made time for one-on-one meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://knowyourteam.com/&quot;&gt;Know Your Team&lt;/a&gt;, a software company focused on team development, did a survey in 2018 with a similar result: they surveyed 1182 managers and 838 employees, and found that 89% of the managers and 73% of the employees said that one-on-ones positively affected a team’s performance. However, 40% of employees think their manager isn’t prepared for one-on-one meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;engagement-through-dialogue&quot;&gt;Engagement through dialogue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ongoing dialogue creates engagement. Dialogue is an opportunity for managers to show they care about their team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Don Clifton in the book &lt;em&gt;First, Break All the Rules: What the world’s Greatest Managers Do Differently&lt;/em&gt;, caring is one of the twelve key items to measure the strength of a workplace. But to show they care, managers need to listen to employees’ answers. Kurt Deenan, a Gallup consultant, &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/businessjournal/147749/value-conversations-employees.aspx&quot;&gt;says&lt;/a&gt; “managers need to listen to their employees, not just talk at their team. Managers create a sense of engagement through conversation.” Communication problems are often the cause of why teams have a low perception of how much their opinion counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That does not necessarily need to happen in a formal one-on-one meeting. It may happen through serendipitous encounters. Managers need to be listening all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one-on-one meetings are remarkable to gauge an employee’s sense of connection and set expectations. It’s a suitable way to know the person’s strengths, thus making it easier to match their talents to a role and increasing performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-conduct-a-one-on-one-meeting&quot;&gt;How to conduct a one-on-one meeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;block-your-schedule&quot;&gt;Block your schedule&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the frequency you hold one-on-one meetings vary according to the size of the team, the experience of the employees or even the distance in the org chart (it’s unlikely the CTO will hold as many one-on-ones with the developers as their direct managers will), it’s important to keep them recurring. Experiment with the frequency, but do not cancel the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-prepared&quot;&gt;Be prepared&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s your employees’ meeting, they should bring a list of points to discuss, but that doesn’t mean you shouldn’t be prepared. In the ideal scenario, both of you would work jointly on an agenda, but in case that’s not possible, write down your own list too. Compare the lists, prioritize and make sure you cover the most critical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-present&quot;&gt;Be present&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turn off your notifications and close your notebook. If it’s in a remote environment, block off distractions, let your video call software fullscreen and pay attention. The only exception is if you agree with your employee you’re taking notes in the meeting. That being so, split the screen with only your video call software and your note-taking application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-not-use-it-as-a-status-report-meeting&quot;&gt;Do not use it as a status report meeting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use one-on-one meetings to solve problems, but keep it as a more strategic problem-solving. It’s not a status report meeting, if you need to learn the status of some task, use a work management software (such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pipefy.com&quot;&gt;Pipefy&lt;/a&gt;) and check there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ask-open-ended-questions&quot;&gt;Ask open-ended questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good open-ended questions lead to substantial answers. A “how are you?” question seems vague, try instead asking specific questions with open-end answers. For instance, “what’s the favorite part of what you do and what’s the least desirable one?” followed by a “why is that so?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important you keep a record of the meetings so you don’t miss anything. If you constantly miss what your employee is saying, you send the wrong message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several tools that can assist in your one-on-one meeting. You can keep a shared document on Google Docs or other office tools (remember you can also have your private notes), but you can also take advantage of your work management tool. Using Pipefy, you can set up a one-on-one pipe (there’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pipefy.com/templates/one-one-meeting/&quot;&gt;template&lt;/a&gt; for that) to keep track of every meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the office, it’s easier to have water cooler chats and serendipitous encounters where you can start building relationships with the team. In a remote environment, we need to rely on other methods to build those connections. One-on-one meetings are one of those ways and it’s highly associated with the effectiveness of a manager by their employees. There’s no exact formula for a successful meeting, but some simple rules make it more fruitful. Engage the team and see a boost in productivity and morale. Trust me, I know what I’m saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@charlesdeluvio?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Charles Deluvio&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Douglas Drumond Kayama</name></author><summary type="html">You can’t simply gain trust by saying “trust me, I know what I’m saying”, you have to earn it. Let’s start discussing trust and then how to conduct one-on-one meetings to earn that trust.</summary></entry></feed>