<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>events on Douglas Drumond Kayama</title><link>https://douglasdrumond.tech/tags/events/</link><description>Recent content in events on Douglas Drumond Kayama</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://douglasdrumond.tech/tags/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>GDG Talks #1</title><link>https://douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-03-16-gdg-talks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-03-16-gdg-talks/</guid><description>Usually every month we have an informal meeting at GDG Campinas, where we gather and discuss whatever comes to mind (most of the time it’s Android, the preferred topic for most of the attendees), but this month we decided to do something different.
Organized by Karuan Bertoluci, this month meeting was a series of three talks hosted at Ci&amp;amp;T, which provided the venue and some beverage and food.
After Karuan opened the event, I gave the first talk on Android Wear.</description></item><item><title>FLISOL Campinas - Uploaded talks</title><link>https://douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-04-28-flisol-campinas/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-04-28-flisol-campinas/</guid><description>Yesterday I presented 4 talks at FLISOL Campinas and I uploaded three of them online. The event was in Portuguese, so is the rest of this post.
Ontem apresentei 4 palestras no FLISOL Campinas. Subi 3 palestras online, uma em HTML5 aqui nesse mesmo site, as outras no SlideShare.
Palestras apresentadas Android Faixa Branca Essa foi uma palestra de introdução ao Android, apresentando conceitos básicos e um exemplo de aplicativo.</description></item><item><title>DevFestW Campinas</title><link>https://douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-04-11-devfestw-campinas/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-04-11-devfestw-campinas/</guid><description>What is DevFestW? Quoting the main site:
DevFestW is a series of community-led events that have technical sessions centered around Google developer technologies and platforms. DevFestW is focused specifically on bringing together women in the local developer community to teach, learn, code and network.
DevFestW Campinas DevFestWs were supposed to be held in March, but we had to postpone ours to yesterday (April 10th) because of some problems with location. Finally, we got a lot of support from Dextraining to promote the event, from food to location, to video cameras to record the event, so we decided to do it even so late.</description></item></channel></rss>