<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Douglas Drumond Kayama</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Douglas Drumond Kayama</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 03:47:29 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Vim was a big part of my life</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2023-08-20-a-sad-email/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 03:47:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2023-08-20-a-sad-email/</guid><description>:e a-sad-email.md
I opened MacVim to tell a personal story.
The year was 1998, I was 15. I told my dad I wanted to go to a certification program. It&amp;rsquo;s something familiar in Brazil; you have high school courses and earn a certificate in parallel. I was inclined to study Chemistry (I really enjoyed the subject back then), but someone had suggested Informatics, and it looked promising. One problem: I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a computer and had no money to buy one.</description></item><item><title>iPad Incompatibilities: Unintuitive Volume Buttons</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-12-28-ipad-incompatibilities/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 23:41:03 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-12-28-ipad-incompatibilities/</guid><description>The iPad is a useful tool. I have two, the ginormous 12.9” iPad Pro and an iPad mini, and I enjoy both. Each has its use case.
The Pro is used for consuming videos, photo editing, reading photography magazines and books, writing, and other activities that benefit from a large screen and, sometimes, a calibrated screen, such as when you enable the reference mode in settings.
The mini is used for quick consumption here and there.</description></item><item><title>How to boost your creativity</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-02-07-how-to-boost-your-creativity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 21:38:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-02-07-how-to-boost-your-creativity/</guid><description>A friend of mine shared with me two talks on different processes leading to creativity. A 2016 TEDx talk by futurist Stephan Schwartz and a 2019 TED talk by author Tim Harford. While Stephan Schwartz presents a process divided into six steps to induce creativity, Tim Harford shows a different method, much more diverse in approach. Comparing both processes, they seem conflicting; however, when analysing more closely, they complement each other.</description></item><item><title>Opportunity Solution Tree</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-01-13-opportunity-solution-tree/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 23:26:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-01-13-opportunity-solution-tree/</guid><description>Have you ever tried to brainstorm ideas to find what to work on next? And you ended up with too many ideas that you had to aggressively trim down or, worse, you solved the wrong problem? Opportunity Solution Tree may help you avoid that.
Opportunity Solution Tree (let&amp;rsquo;s shorten it to OST) is a visual way to represent how the solutions connect to the desired outcome in a way that helps you focus on solving the right problem.</description></item><item><title>Extreme Ownership</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-01-12-extreme-ownership/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 12:45:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-01-12-extreme-ownership/</guid><description>When I first got a leadership role, I asked a friend for tips to learn and do my job better. He referred me to a book, Extreme Ownership, by Jocko Willink and Leif Babin.
The book’s main idea is to take ownership of everything you do (or don’t do), especially for a leader. If a team fails, the leader should step up and assume the failure instead of blaming the team.</description></item><item><title>Gear with soul</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-01-08-gear-with-soul/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 23:12:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-01-08-gear-with-soul/</guid><description>Does gear have a soul?
Recently I watched a YouTube video from Ted Vieira, a well-known photographer among the Fujifilm community, titled Gear With Soul? He shows a magazine by KEH Camera with the tagline &amp;ldquo;Gear with soul for people with vision&amp;rdquo; and spends the video showing photos and talking about that.
There&amp;rsquo;s also an old video from DigitalRev TV where Kai Wong discusses what makes a Leica M unique. And the very last line is &amp;ldquo;it got soul.</description></item><item><title>Working through change</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-01-05-working-through-change/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 23:12:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2022-01-05-working-through-change/</guid><description>“It’s not the strongest of the species that survives, nor the most intelligent; it is the most adaptable to change.” This quote is often misattributed to Charles Darwin (it first appeared in a speech by Leon C. Megginson in 1963).
That quote refers to the evolution of the species, but we can bring it to the corporate environment, especially in the startup world. Companies pivot. Companies fail. Companies merge and get acquired—the culture of the company changes.</description></item><item><title>One-on-one meetings</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2021-03-28-one-on-one-meetings/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 21:38:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2021-03-28-one-on-one-meetings/</guid><description>You can&amp;rsquo;t simply gain trust by saying “trust me, I know what I&amp;rsquo;m saying”, you have to earn it. Let&amp;rsquo;s start discussing trust and then how to conduct one-on-one meetings to earn that trust.
Trust In The High Price of Mistrust, a book titled Bowling Alone, by Robert Putnam, is discussed and there are two parts I&amp;rsquo;d like to quote as they relate to remote management:
“One key lesson we can derive from Bowling Alone is that the less we trust each other—something which is both a cause and consequence of declining community engagement—the more it costs us.</description></item><item><title>Movile Meetup</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-06-29-movile-meetup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-06-29-movile-meetup/</guid><description>Movile has a new initiative called Movile Meetups. Every once in a while someone either from Movile or outside (for now, we had only two talks and both were from Movile employees) presents something and it’s open for the local community to participate, not only Movile employees. The talk usually lasts for forty minutes, then there’s a Q&amp;amp;A session and finally we go to the Recharging Area (our kitchen) to eat pizza, drink beer and soda and talk to each other.</description></item><item><title>Technically Speaking hangout on LAtINiTY conference</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-05-19-technically-speaking/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-05-19-technically-speaking/</guid><description>TL;DR: Technically Speaking is hosting a webinar on LAtINiTY conference and you should watch. Signup here.
Do you know Technically Speaking? It&amp;rsquo;s a great newsletter with tips to improve your tech talks, inspirational videos and call for papers delivered direct to your inbox. This newsletter is provided by Chiu-Ki Chan (site, Google Plus and Twitter) and Cate Huston (site, Google Plus and Twitter).
For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know them, let me give a brief introdution:</description></item><item><title>Tips for Android beginners</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-04-04-tips-for-android-beginners/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-04-04-tips-for-android-beginners/</guid><description>A while ago someone asked on Quora how to learn Android development. The person had knowledge of Java, but none of XML. I suppose the fear of XML came from the fact that is well known that Android uses a lot of XML. I started with a quick clarification on XML syntax and that&amp;rsquo;s the only required knowledge of XML. The parsing is done automatically by the Android system or the build tools.</description></item><item><title>GDG Talks #1</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-03-16-gdg-talks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-03-16-gdg-talks/</guid><description>Usually every month we have an informal meeting at GDG Campinas, where we gather and discuss whatever comes to mind (most of the time it’s Android, the preferred topic for most of the attendees), but this month we decided to do something different.
Organized by Karuan Bertoluci, this month meeting was a series of three talks hosted at Ci&amp;amp;T, which provided the venue and some beverage and food.
After Karuan opened the event, I gave the first talk on Android Wear.</description></item><item><title>Messing MacVim</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-03-06-messing-macvim/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-03-06-messing-macvim/</guid><description>I published a new version of MacVim on last week Monday and was quite happy with it. It was early morning, I published it at 7:30 AM (UTC-3) and went to work. Of course, being an avid user of Vim, the first thing I did at work was updating my copy of MacVim.
Then things went awry. MacVim crashed at launch (of course, it didn’t occur at home). E-mails started popping on my inbox.</description></item><item><title>MacVim is back on track</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-02-23-MacVim-is-back-on-track.md/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2015-02-23-MacVim-is-back-on-track.md/</guid><description>It’s no secret I’m a big fan of Vim. Although I can use it in the terminal, I like to have a nice UI to look at and when I’m on a Mac (e.g., at work), I use MacVim. I have no words to thank the amazing job behind both Vim and MacVim and I always wanted to contribute back.
I’ve been building MacVim for older versions of Mac since 2012 and since Björn has been busy, I’m maintaining it now.</description></item><item><title>3.11</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2014-03-12-3-11/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2014-03-12-3-11/</guid><description>Three years ago, on March 11th, a tsunami hit the east coast of Japan killing 19000 people and leaving many others homeless. Still today many of them can’t return to their home due to radiation near Fukushima disaster. Yahoo!Japan had a great initiative, donating 10 yen for each search for “3.11”
See the announcement: http://promo.search.yahoo.co.jp/searchfor311/ and the video below:</description></item><item><title>Happy Birthday, WWW</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2014-03-12-happy-birthday-www/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2014-03-12-happy-birthday-www/</guid><description>25 years ago, Sir Tim Berners-Lee created the World Wide Web, read about it on Computer History Museum.
Seeing the pictures makes me nostalgic. I used WindowMaker when I started using Linux in 1999 and it’s inspired by NeXTSTEP.
Update:
Another legendary Tim made a nice post: https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2014/03/11/The-Web-is-25 (that’s Tim Bray, co-creator of XML).
Also, celebrate at http://www.webat25.org/</description></item><item><title>Understanding Android Open Source Project</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2014-02-27-understanding-aosp/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2014-02-27-understanding-aosp/</guid><description>A while ago someone asked on Quora about some good ways to understand the AOSP. Although I don’t work with Android internals anymore, it was fun looking back into AOSP and finding some sources (no pun intended). Here’s my answer (edited for this blog):
Obviously, first go to AOSP site and follow the instructions to download the source.
Although outdated, take a look at Android Platform Developer’s Guide (it’s a copy of the old PDK, removed from Android site now).</description></item><item><title>The Setup</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2014-02-23-the-setup/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2014-02-23-the-setup/</guid><description>There are a lot of posts about how someone uses their computer to get the job done. One of my favorite sites that compiles a list of posts like that is The Setup. As I like to keep track of what I use, I’m doing my own The Setup-like post to open this blog.
Who are you, and what do you do? I’m Douglas Drumond, Android developer at Movile and organizer of GDG Campinas.</description></item><item><title>My Git Workflow</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-07-20-my-git-workflow/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-07-20-my-git-workflow/</guid><description>Proceeding with my sequence of posts about version control systems, I’ll explain my Git workflow. It’s quite simple, after set up, the day to day workflow is as follows:
get the latest information from remote server: git pull --ff-only create a new branch and switch to it: git checkout -b branch_name work, work, work, then commit: git commit go back to master: git checkout master check if there’s something new: git pull --ff-only merge my work back into master: git rebase branch_name upload the modifications to server: git push And since I reached the magic number seven, those are the seven steps.</description></item><item><title>Version Control Systems</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-07-17-version-control-system/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-07-17-version-control-system/</guid><description>A while ago, Fábio Akita from AkitaOnRails.com launched the campaign “Beginners’s Friday” intended to help the new generation of developers coming today. I’m totally buying into this idea and this is the first post I’m doing in that direction with version control systems.
Version Control Systems What is a version control system? In the context of software development, a version control, revision control or source control system is a software designed to control changes to computer programs (as well as documents, sites and virtually whatever you want).</description></item><item><title>DevFestW Campinas</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-04-11-devfestw-campinas/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-04-11-devfestw-campinas/</guid><description>What is DevFestW? Quoting the main site:
DevFestW is a series of community-led events that have technical sessions centered around Google developer technologies and platforms. DevFestW is focused specifically on bringing together women in the local developer community to teach, learn, code and network.
DevFestW Campinas DevFestWs were supposed to be held in March, but we had to postpone ours to yesterday (April 10th) because of some problems with location. Finally, we got a lot of support from Dextraining to promote the event, from food to location, to video cameras to record the event, so we decided to do it even so late.</description></item><item><title>Waza Opening</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-03-01-waza-opening/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2013-03-01-waza-opening/</guid><description>Waza is an event promoted by Heroku, a PaaS company. In Ruby language world there is this tendency to name things after Japanese words (Ruby itself came from Japan, thanks to Matsumoto Yukihiro, a.k.a. Matz), although I have no idea if this influenced Heroku somehow. Heroku itself I don’t think it’s a Japanese word (at least I couldn’t find it in any dictionary I looked at). On the other hand, waza is a Japanese word meanining technique, so it makes perfect sense to name an event focused on technical knowledge after this word.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on DevFest Brasil</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-12-02-devfest-brasil/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-12-02-devfest-brasil/</guid><description>Last Friday I went to DevFest Brasil (in Portuguese). Since Google won’t promote Google Developer Day anymore, the Google Developer Groups (former GTUG, Google Technology User Groups) are promoting DevFest. So, these events, instead of being backed up by a big company, are from community to community. I recognize the hassle that is promoting these, and I think the people from GDG-SP (São Paulo), GDG-BH (Belo Horizonte) and GDG-GO (Goiás) did a great job nonetheless.</description></item><item><title>My talk from DevFest Brasil is online</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-30-slides/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-30-slides/</guid><description>I just uploaded the slides of my talk in DevFest Brasil. See link on this page (if you’re on desktop, it should be on the right, if you’re on a smartphone, it’s at the bottom). It’s exactly as I presented. Later today or tomorrow I’ll add some presenter notes or some screenshots of the hands-on part.
Edit: just see the talks page</description></item><item><title>I’ll talk in DevFest Brasil</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-24-devfest/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-24-devfest/</guid><description>This year we won’t have Google Developer Day. Instead, Google Developer Groups are organizing their own events called DevFest. These are pretty much like Google Developer Day with some extras. For instance, in GDDs, we didn’t have codelabs with hands on, just 1h (approx) long talks about a variety of topics Google related.
One other thing that changed are the speakers. On GDD, all were Google Employees or invited by Google.</description></item><item><title>Evernote Hackathon Brazil</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-14-evernote-hackathon-brazil/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-14-evernote-hackathon-brazil/</guid><description>Last weekend (Nov 10–11), Evernote held the second edition of Evernote Hackathon Brazil. It was my first 24H hackathon and it was very exciting. I had participated in two hackathons before, but the doors were shut down at night.
The trip The hackathon was held in São Paulo city at Academia Wayra, a startup incubator located in a very cool building with a nice view. It was the first time Pinheiros river looked nice.</description></item><item><title>Migrating and pruning repos</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-08-migrating-and-pruning-repos/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-08-migrating-and-pruning-repos/</guid><description>Recently I had to put a folder from my app repository into a separate repository on its own. The easiest way was just git init a new repo, copy the directory and git commit it, but I would lose all history up until the move. After fiddling with git and Stack Overflow, I found the solution.
Suppose the structure is like this:
All-in-one repo: * server * code.go * code2.go * iOS * code.</description></item><item><title>Replacing in bash without sed</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-06-bash-replace-without-sed/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-06-bash-replace-without-sed/</guid><description>Bash has built-in substitution. For simple tasks it’s easier than piping through sed:
text=&amp;#34;hello world&amp;#34; echo ${text/hello/ohayou} # prints ohayou world Be aware that just the first word is changed:
text=&amp;#34;hello world hello&amp;#34; echo ${text/hello/ohayou} # prints ohayou world hello To change all instances of a world, prepend the search pattern with another slash:
text=&amp;#34;hello world hello&amp;#34; echo ${text//hello/ohayou} # prints ohayou world ohayou Notice there are two slashes before hello, one as the separator and one prepending it.</description></item><item><title>Eigenclass</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-04-03-eigenclass/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2010 17:33:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-04-03-eigenclass/</guid><description>In Ruby, there’s the concept of eigenclasses, or singleton classes. These are classes implicitly defined when attaching methods to a single instance.
From Wikipedia:
Ruby is object-oriented: every data type is an object, including classes and types which many other languages designate as primitives (such as integers, booleans, and &amp;ldquo;nil&amp;rdquo;). Every function is a method. Named values (variables) always designate references to objects, not the objects themselves. Ruby supports inheritance with dynamic dispatch, mixins and singleton methods (belonging to, and defined for, a single instance rather than being defined on the class).</description></item><item><title>The Coffee Song</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-02-28-the-coffee-song/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2010 15:30:54 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-02-28-the-coffee-song/</guid><description>Frank Steinhoff suggested this Sinatra’s song. It’s about coffee and Brazil and it would have arise in a coffee talk at IMECC’s coffee room.
Way down among brazilians
Coffee beans grow by the billions
So they’ve got to find those extra cups to fill
They’ve got an awful lot of coffee in Brazil
You can’t get cherry soda’cause they’ve got to sell that quota
And the way things are I’ll bet they never will</description></item><item><title>A romance of many dimensions</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-02-28-a-romance-of-many-dimensions/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2010 15:22:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-02-28-a-romance-of-many-dimensions/</guid><description>Editor’s note:This is a guest post from Luciana Takata.
Last week I read for the second time Flatland − a romance of many dimensions (Edwin A. Abbot, 1884). No matter how many times I read this book I guess I’ll never stop finding it interesting.
In Flatland, its inhabitants − triangles, squares, pentagons and other two-dimensional geometrical figures − can only move to right, left, forward, backward or its composed directions.</description></item><item><title>Problem solving, artificial intelligence and computational linear algebra</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-02-25-problem-solving-artificial-intelligence-and-linear-algebra/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2010 07:23:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-02-25-problem-solving-artificial-intelligence-and-linear-algebra/</guid><description>When students come to computer science, it’s hard to motivate them to learn fundamental mathematics subjects such as linear algebra and numerical calculus. In this post I intend to spark this motivation through AI and sketch a method (and some variations) to solve optimization problems.
It’s hard to define AI. We know what artificial means, but what about intelligence? Russel and Norvig [1] present us four approaches to AI: systems that think like humans, systems that think rationally, systems that act like humans and systems that act rationally.</description></item><item><title>Engineering Paradise</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-02-23-engineering-paradise/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2010 02:23:01 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2010-02-23-engineering-paradise/</guid><description>Edit: this is another restored old post.
This is old, but I think it’s so funny and propelling to study I feel I must share it.
This video was made by a colleague, John Cohn, at IBM as a contest for choosing best video to encourage young people to go into engineering and computer science. He made it for fun, since he couldn’t take part at contest as he was organizing it, but he felt it would be good to create something to use as example.</description></item></channel></rss>