<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>git on Café Linear</title><link>https://www.cafelinear.com/tags/git/</link><description>Recent content in git on Café Linear</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.cafelinear.com/tags/git/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>My Git Workflow</title><link>https://www.cafelinear.com/post/2013-07-20-my-git-workflow/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.cafelinear.com/post/2013-07-20-my-git-workflow/</guid><description>Proceeding with my sequence of posts about version control systems, I’ll explain my Git workflow. It’s quite simple, after set up, the day to day workflow is as follows:
get the latest information from remote server: git pull --ff-only create a new branch and switch to it: git checkout -b branch_name work, work, work, then commit: git commit go back to master: git checkout master check if there’s something new: git pull --ff-only merge my work back into master: git rebase branch_name upload the modifications to server: git push And since I reached the magic number seven, those are the seven steps.</description></item><item><title>Version Control Systems</title><link>https://www.cafelinear.com/post/2013-07-17-version-control-system/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.cafelinear.com/post/2013-07-17-version-control-system/</guid><description>A while ago, Fábio Akita from AkitaOnRails.com launched the campaign “Beginners’s Friday” intended to help the new generation of developers coming today. I’m totally buying into this idea and this is the first post I’m doing in that direction with version control systems.
Version Control Systems What is a version control system? In the context of software development, a version control, revision control or source control system is a software designed to control changes to computer programs (as well as documents, sites and virtually whatever you want).</description></item><item><title>Migrating and pruning repos</title><link>https://www.cafelinear.com/post/2012-11-08-migrating-and-pruning-repos/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.cafelinear.com/post/2012-11-08-migrating-and-pruning-repos/</guid><description>Recently I had to put a folder from my app repository into a separate repository on its own. The easiest way was just git init a new repo, copy the directory and git commit it, but I would lose all history up until the move. After fiddling with git and Stack Overflow, I found the solution.
Suppose the structure is like this:
All-in-one repo: * server * code.go * code2.go * iOS * code.</description></item></channel></rss>