<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Android on Douglas Drumond Kayama</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/tags/Android/</link><description>Recent content in Android on Douglas Drumond Kayama</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/tags/Android/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Thoughts on DevFest Brasil</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-12-02-devfest-brasil/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-12-02-devfest-brasil/</guid><description>Last Friday I went to DevFest Brasil (in Portuguese). Since Google won’t promote Google Developer Day anymore, the Google Developer Groups (former GTUG, Google Technology User Groups) are promoting DevFest. So, these events, instead of being backed up by a big company, are from community to community. I recognize the hassle that is promoting these, and I think the people from GDG-SP (São Paulo), GDG-BH (Belo Horizonte) and GDG-GO (Goiás) did a great job nonetheless.</description></item><item><title>My talk from DevFest Brasil is online</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-30-slides/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-30-slides/</guid><description>I just uploaded the slides of my talk in DevFest Brasil. See link on this page (if you’re on desktop, it should be on the right, if you’re on a smartphone, it’s at the bottom). It’s exactly as I presented. Later today or tomorrow I’ll add some presenter notes or some screenshots of the hands-on part.
Edit: just see the talks page</description></item><item><title>I’ll talk in DevFest Brasil</title><link>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-24-devfest/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.douglasdrumond.tech/post/2012-11-24-devfest/</guid><description>This year we won’t have Google Developer Day. Instead, Google Developer Groups are organizing their own events called DevFest. These are pretty much like Google Developer Day with some extras. For instance, in GDDs, we didn’t have codelabs with hands on, just 1h (approx) long talks about a variety of topics Google related.
One other thing that changed are the speakers. On GDD, all were Google Employees or invited by Google.</description></item></channel></rss>